According to an old folk saying,
昔[むかし]:olden days/former, 言葉[ことば, けとば]:language|word|speech, 本来[ほんらい]:originally|essentially|proper
（ヤサコ）
昔の人の言葉によると 本来―
normally, people are supposed to know what path they should pursue.
必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, 進む[すすむ]:to advance|to precede|to make progress||, 進む[すさむ]:to grow wild/to run to waste, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||
人は必ず自分の進むべき道を
知っているそうです
一番[いちばん]:number one|best|game||, 一番[ひとつがい]:pair/couple/brace, 大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect), 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||, 見失う[みうしなう]:to lose sight of/to miss
でも 一番 大事な道こそ
見失いがちなのだそうです
But despite this,
they tend to lose sight of the most important path.
（ヤサコ）ハラケン
（ハラケン）フミエは？
Haraken!
Where's Fumie?
学習塾[がくしゅうじゅく]:private night-school/tutoring school (math, English, etc.)
学習塾だって
She said she had prep school.
将来[しょうらい]:future (usually near)/prospects, 道に迷う[みちにまよう]:to lose one's way/to get lost
将来 道に迷いたくないんだってさ
"I don't want to lose sight of my path in the future," she said.
日記[にっき]:diary/journal, 解析[かいせき]:analysis/analytical study|parsing
あれから 日記の解析はどう？
How's the analysis of the diary coming along?
見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||, 先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.), 必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, イリーガル:illegal, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
（ハラケン）
カンナが見つけた道の先には
必ずイリーガルがいたらしい
It's almost certain that at the end of the path Kanna was following,
there was an Illegal.
イリーガル:illegal, 意外[いがい]:unexpected/surprising
（ヤサコ）
イリーガルって意外といるのね
There sure are a lot more different types of Illegals than you'd expect...
魚[さかな, うお]:fish, 次々[つぎつぎ]:in succession/one by one, 現れる[あらわれる]:to appear/to come in sight|to be expressed (e.g. emotions), 驚く[おどろく]:to be surprised/to be astonished
魚にヒゲと
次々 現れたときは驚いたわ
I was surprised to see how many of them exist. The fish, the Bearded Ones...
Yeah.
見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
まだ誰も見つけていない空間が
あるのかもしれないね
And let's not forget that there are Spaces no one's even discovered yet.
霧[きり]:fog/mist|spray
あった 霧だ
Here it is. The fog.
（ヤサコ）あっ キュウちゃんだわ
Kyuu-chans!
（ハラケン）何をしているんだ？
What are they doing?
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||, 消去[しょうきょ]:elimination/erasure/dying out
古い空間への道を消去しているんだ
So they're deleting access to the obsolete Space.
急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten, 他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), 当たる[あたる]:to be hit|to touch|to be equivalent to||
急いで 他も当たってみましょう
（ハラケン）うん
Let's hurry and try somewhere else!
よーし:alright/all right/right on, ご苦労[ごくろう]:trouble (I have put you through)
（オバちゃん）
よーしよし ご苦労さん
Good, good! Great job!
調子[ちょうし]:tune|vein|condition||, ガンガン:sound of large bell/sound of scolding voice/(pounding of) headache, 初期化[しょきか]:initialization/initialisation|formatting, してやる:to do for (someone)
この調子で
ガンガン初期化してやる
At this rate, I can definitely reformat all areas.
日記[にっき]:diary/journal, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||
（ハラケン）
カンナの日記にあった道は
This is the last route
The Last Plesiosaur
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments
これが最後だ
Kanna jotted down in her diary.
ハラケン 見て！
Haraken, look!
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
（ハラケン）古い空間だ
（ヤサコ）まだあった
It's an obsolete Space!
So there was another one!
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength), 霧[きり]:fog/mist|spray
（ヤサコ）すごい霧
What amazing fog!
あら？
Oh?
自転車[じてんしゃ, じでんしゃ]:bicycle
（ハラケン）この自転車は…
This bicycle...
あれ？
Huh?
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception
あれ デンパじゃないか？
Isn't that Denpa?
（ヤサコ）あっ あれは…
And that's...
危ない[あぶない]:dangerous|in danger|uncertain||, デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception
（ハラケン）あっ！
（ヤサコ）危ない デンパ君！
Denpa, watch out!
（デンパ）
えっ？　ハラケン ヤサコ！
Haraken?
Yasako?
逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
に… 逃げて！
R-Run!
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception, 逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
（ヤサコ）
デ… デンパ君こそ逃げて！
D-Denpa, you're the one who should be running!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
（デンパ）早く逃げて！
Run away! Hurry!
逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
えっ？　逃げてって…
So that "run" was...
イリーガル:illegal
イリーガルに言ってたのか？
...meant for the Illegal?
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
（デンパ）
な… 何しに来たの？　早く帰って
What are you doing here?
Go home, quickly!
Denpa, what on earth are you doing?
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception
デンパ君こそ何してるの？
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
（ハラケン）まさか…
Don't tell me...
イリーガル:illegal, 飼う[かう]:to keep (a pet or other animal)/to raise/to have, デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception
イ… イリーガルを飼ってるの？
デンパ君
...y-you're raising an Illegal?!
呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
（デンパ）クビナガって呼んでる
I named it Plesio.
Don't tell anyone, please?
内緒[ないしょ, ないしょう]:secrecy|one's circumstances (esp. fiscal)|inner realization|
誰にも言わないでね
ダイチにも内緒だよ
Not even Daichi.
約束[やくそく]:promise|convention|destiny
（ハラケン）うん
（ヤサコ）約束する
Sure. It's a promise.
イリーガル:illegal, 飼う[かう]:to keep (a pet or other animal)/to raise/to have, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
（ヤサコ）それにしても
イリーガルを飼うなんて
Of all things, Denpa...
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception, すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength)
デンパ君ってすごいわね
It's amazing that you're raising an Illegal.
ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET
別にペットってわけじゃないんだ
It's not a pet or anything.
懐く[なつく, なずく]:to become emotionally attached, 懐く[いだく, だく]:to embrace|to harbour (e.g. grudge)|to have sex with|, 時々[ときどき]:sometimes/at times
エサをやってるうちに懐いてきて
時々 会ってるんだ
All I did was feed it, but at some point it became attached to me,
so I visit it sometimes.
イリーガル:illegal
でも イリーガルであるからには…
But it's an Illegal!
そうだ これは聞かなきゃ
Right, I need to ask you.
Huh?
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||, イリーガル:illegal, 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
（ヤサコ）
私たち 電脳ナビの事故に関係した
イリーガルを探してるの
We're looking for the Illegal involved in the cybernavi accident.
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
まさか このクビナガは―
By any chance, does Plesio
ドメイン:domain, 接続[せつぞく]:connection|changing trains|conjunction
ナビのドメインに
接続したりしてない？
connect to a cybernavi domain?
うーん:hmm/well
（デンパ）
うーん… よく分かんないけど
I don't know,
壊す[こわす]:to break|to wreck|to break (a bill, etc.), 狂う[くるう]:to go mad|to get out of order/to go amiss, 一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree
何かを壊したり
車を狂わせたことは一度もないよ
but it never broke anything,
nor did it make any cars break down.
食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off
メタバグしか食べないし
All it eats are metabugs.
（ハラケン）そうか
I see...
一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree, 小さい[ちいさい]:small/little/tiny, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, 連れる[つれる]:to lead/to take (a person)
一度 小さい電脳ペットを
連れた人が―
I remember one time someone brought their cyberpet here,
ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions
ここに来たことがあったけど
先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.), 逃げ出す[にげだす]:to run away/to flee|to start to run away
こいつのほうが
先に逃げ出しちゃって
and the one who ran away was Plesio!
おとなしい:obedient/docile/quiet
おとなしいヤツなんだ
It's so docile.
最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first, 大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great
最初から こんなに大きかったの？
Has it always been this big?
ううん:no|er, well, ..., 初め[はじめ]:beginning|first (in line, etc.)|origin|, 初め[ぞめ]:first doing of ... (ever, in one's life, in the new year, etc.), もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 小さい[ちいさい]:small/little/tiny
ううん 初めは
もっと小さかったんだよ
No, in the beginning it was much smaller.
最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first, 小さな[ちいさな]:small/little/tiny, 匹[ひき, き]:counter for small animals|counter for rolls of cloth (two han in size)|counter for horses|
最初 見たとき
小さな１匹だけが―
When I first saw it,
it was this small, exhausted-looking thing sticking out of the ground.
グラウンド:sports ground/sports oval, はみ出す[はみだす]:to protrude/to stick out/to hang out
グラウンドから はみ出して
グッタリしてたんだ
それが クビナガだったんだ
That's how it was when I found it.
グラウンド:sports ground/sports oval, 奥[おく]:inner part/inside/interior, もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, たくさん:a lot/lots|enough
見ると グラウンドの奥に
もっとたくさんいて
When I looked around, I saw more of them on the lot too.
ビックリ:to be surprised/to be amazed/to be frightened, 声を上げる[こえをあげる]:to raise one's voice, そいつ:he/she|that, 逃げ出す[にげだす]:to run away/to flee|to start to run away
ビックリして声を上げたら
そいつらも逃げ出して…
I was scared, so I screamed out,
but they ran away.
偶然[ぐうぜん]:coincidence|by chance|contingency (philosophy), 落とす[おとす]:to drop|to clean off (dirt, makeup, paint, etc.)|to lose (a match)||, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off
そのとき 僕が 偶然 落とした
メタバグを食べたんだ
At that moment, I accidentally dropped some metabugs, and it ate them,
集める[あつめる]:to collect/to assemble/to gather, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off, させる:to make (someone) do|to allow (someone) to, させる:(usu. followed by a negative form) worth special consideration
それで
クズバグを集めて食べさせたら
so I collected a few rubbishbugs to feed it with.
元気[げんき]:lively/full of spirit|healthy, グラウンド:sports ground/sports oval, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
元気になって
グラウンドに戻ったんだ
It recovered slightly, then went back into the lot.
（ハラケン）いつからなの？
When was this?
半年[はんとし, はんねん]:half year
（デンパ）半年ほど前
About half a year ago.
内緒[ないしょ, ないしょう]:secrecy|one's circumstances (esp. fiscal)|inner realization|
ダイチにも内緒にしてたんだよ
I didn't even tell Daichi.
だんだん:gradually/by degrees|steps, だんだん:thank you (dialect from the Izumo region of Shimane Prefecture), 数[しばしば]:often/again and again/frequently, 数[かず]:number/amount, 減る[へる]:to decrease (in size or number)/to diminish/to abate, 結局[けっきょく]:after all|conclusion|ending of a game of Go, 以外[いがい]:with the exception of/excepting
でも だんだん数が減って
結局 クビナガ以外は みんな…
But their numbers gradually declined.
In the end, all the Plesios...
昔[むかし]:olden days/former, 大きな[おおきな]:big/large/great, 生き物[いきもの]:living thing/animal, 憧れる[あこがれる]:to long for/to yearn after/to admire
僕 昔から
大きな生き物に憧れてて
I always liked big creatures,
出会う[であう]:to meet (by chance)|to meet (e.g. of rivers, highways, etc.)|to emerge and engage (an enemy)
クビナガに出会ったときも
so when we walked together after we met,
恐竜[きょうりゅう]:dinosaur, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, ながら:while/during|while, 歩く[あるく]:to walk
恐竜のことを考えながら
歩いてたんだ
it reminded me of a dinosaur.
願い[ねがい]:desire/wish/request, かなう:to come true (wish)|to be suited, たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however
願いがかなったってわけね
In a way, your dream has come true.
仲良し[なかよし]:intimate friend/close friend/bosom buddy
うん だから
すぐに仲良しになれたんだ
Yup.
That's why we became friends so easily.
大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
でも こいつは ちょっと
大きくなりすぎちゃったかな
But I think this guy's grown too big.
最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first, 一番[いちばん]:number one|best|game||, 一番[ひとつがい]:pair/couple/brace, 小さい[ちいさい]:small/little/tiny
最初は一番小さかったくせに
And to think that it was the smallest one to begin with!
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 魚[さかな, うお]:fish, どんどん:drumming (noise)|rapidly/steadily, 大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great
（ヤサコ）
そういえば この間の魚も
どんどん大きくなったわ
Now that you mention it,
that fish from awhile back also kept growing bigger and bigger.
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 大きさ[おおきさ]:size/dimensions/volume, 制御[せいぎょ]:control/governing/checking, プログラム:program/programme, バグる:to behave buggily (software)/to act up/to behave strangely
（ハラケン）
きっと大きさを制御する
プログラムがバグってるんだ
The program that controls their size must have a bug in it.
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), 面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant
バグは他にもあるんだ 面白いよ
There's also another bug.
It's quite interesting.
（デンパ）クビナガ こっちだよ
Plesio, this way.
黒土[こくど, くろつち]:black terracotta/black soil, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, 移動[いどう]:movement/transfer|mobile
（ヤサコ）
黒土の所しか移動できないんだ
Oh, so he can only move along the dark ground.
黒い[くろい]:black|dark|illicit, 部分[ぶぶん]:portion/section/part, 誤認[ごにん]:misrecognition/mistaking (x for y)
（ハラケン）黒い部分を
水のように誤認するバグなんだね
It's a bug that mistakenly reads the dark parts as water.
（ヤサコ）
へえー そんなのあるんだ
Oh, I didn't know such a thing could happen.
白い[しろい]:white, 線[せん]:line|line (e.g. telephone line)|ray (e.g. X-ray)||, コンクリ:concrete, 進める[すすめる]:to advance/to promote/to hasten
そう　だから 白い線や
白いコンクリには進めないんだ
Yeah, and that's why it can't cross white lines or concrete.
How odd.
不思議[ふしぎ]:wonder/miracle/strange, 地面[じめん]:ground/earth's surface, まるで:quite/entirely|as if, 波打つ[なみうつ]:to dash against/to undulate/to wave
（ヤサコ）不思議だわ
地面がまるで水のように波打ってる
The ground has ripples, just like water.
So he doesn't like the sun, either?
当たる[あたる]:to be hit|to touch|to be equivalent to||
日が当たってもダメなの？
Yeah.
グラウンド:sports ground/sports oval
（デンパ）
うん このグラウンドには―
On this lot, there's a spot where the sun never shines.
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 当たる[あたる]:to be hit|to touch|to be equivalent to||, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
一日中 日が当たらない
場所があるんだ
So that's how it's been able to survive.
生き延びる[いきのびる]:to survive/to live long
（ハラケン）
だから 生き延びられたんだね
（ヤサコ）
ヒゲたちのときに思ったんだけど…
Back then, when we met the Bearded Ones, I wondered
イリーガル:illegal, 迷子[まいご]:lost child/lost person/stray child, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
イリーガルたちは
迷子みたいなものじゃないかしら？
if perhaps Illegals are like lost children.
迷子[まいご]:lost child/lost person/stray child
（ハラケン）迷子？
（ヤサコ）そう
Lost children?
Yeah.
I thought, "Maybe what they're looking for is their home,
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
（ヤサコ）だから帰る場所を…
where their family awaits them."
家族[かぞく]:family/members of a family, 故郷[ふるさと, こきょう]:home town/birthplace|ruins, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
家族が待ってる故郷みたいな場所を
探してるんじゃないかって思うの
Family, huh?
家族[かぞく]:family/members of a family, 一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried
家族か…
もう自分一人しかいないのにね
But in reality, it's the last one left.
Its cry is so sad...
I think
人類[じんるい]:mankind/humanity, 死に絶える[しにたえる]:to die out/to become extinct, 生き残る[いきのこる]:to survive, たとする:to appreciate/to be thankful
（ハラケン）もし人類が死に絶えて
自分だけ生き残ったとしたら
that if humankind faced extinction,
and if I were the only one to survive...
...living alone until the very last day
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, 生き残る[いきのこる]:to survive
（ヤサコ）最後まで生き残るのって
would be so miserable.
むしろ:rather/better/instead, むしろ:woven mat (esp. one made of straw)|seat, 悲しい[かなしい]:sad/sorrowful, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
むしろ
悲しいことなのかもしれないわね
（フミエ）ハァー！
I'm tired of studying.
勉強[べんきょう]:study|diligence|discount, 疲れる[つかれる]:to get tired|to be worn out (e.g. of well used objects)|to starve
私 勉強で疲れてんのよ
Where's Haraken?
ハラケンは？
病院[びょういん]:hospital
うん なんか… 病院 行くって
He said he'd be at the hospital.
It's about that dizziness he experienced last time.
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 立ちくらみ[たちくらみ]:dizziness (from standing up too fast)/orthostatic syncope/lightheadedness
（ヤサコ）
この間の立ちくらみのことだってさ
It's so hot I feel like I could have a dizzy spell, too!
暑い[あつい]:hot (weather, etc.)/warm, 立ちくらみ[たちくらみ]:dizziness (from standing up too fast)/orthostatic syncope/lightheadedness
（フミエ）こっちこそ
暑さで立ちくらみしそうよ
Hey, is it still far?
ねえ まだなの？
We're almost there.
（ヤサコ）もうすぐだって
You'll see. You'll be very surprised.
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, ビックリ:to be surprised/to be amazed/to be frightened
きっとビックリするわよ
Nothing surprises me any more.
大抵[たいてい]:mostly|probably|most||, ビックリ:to be surprised/to be amazed/to be frightened
私は もう大抵のことでは
ビックリしないわよ
Okay then, when I tell you, open your eyes.
開ける[あける]:to open (a door, etc.)|to open (for business, etc.)|to empty||, 開ける[ひらける]:to become opened up|to develop|to be enlightened
じゃあ いいって言ったら
目 開けてね
Open them.
いいわよ
ホント:truth/reality/actuality, ビックリ:to be surprised/to be amazed/to be frightened
あら ホントにビックリしないのね
Huh?
So you really don't get surprised any more.
You're amazing, Fumie.
恐れ入る[おそれいる]:to be sorry|to be grateful|to be amazed|
恐れ入ったわ フミエちゃん
She's passed out on her feet.
立つ[たつ]:to stand|to find oneself (e.g. in a difficult position)|to depart (on a plane, train, etc.), 気絶[きぜつ]:faint/swoon
立ったまま気絶してるね
Wh-What was that thing?
（フミエ）な… なんなのよ あれは
So you were surprised after all!
やっぱり:too/also|still, ビックリ:to be surprised/to be amazed/to be frightened, 首長[しゅちょう]:head (of organization, organisation)/chief, 竜[りゅう, たつ]:dragon (esp. a Chinese dragon)|naga|promoted rook, イリーガル:illegal
（ヤサコ）
やっぱりビックリしたでしょ？
首長竜のイリーガルよ
It's a Plesiosaur Illegal.
I can't stand huge things.
大きな[おおきな]:big/large/great, 苦手[にがて]:poor (at)/weak (in)|dislike (of)
私 大きなものは苦手なのよ
And since it's so huge, Satchii will probably be here soon.
大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great, 寄る[よる]:to approach|to gather (in one place)|to stop by (while on one's way to another place)||
でも これだけ大きいと
サッチー寄ってくるんじゃない？
This must be a domain Satchii can't enter.
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||, ドメイン:domain
（ヤサコ）きっと サッチーが
入れないドメインなのよ
管理[かんり]:control/management (e.g. of a business), かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
ここは
どこが管理してるのかしら？
I wonder who's managing this place?
It doesn't really matter who.
管理[かんり]:control/management (e.g. of a business)
どこの管理にしても
A cybersubstance that grows that large becomes quite fragile.
大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time), 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 物質[ぶっしつ]:material/substance|matter, 壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through, やすい:cheap/inexpensive|calm, やすい:easy|likely to .../have a tendency to ...
大きくなりすぎた電脳物質は
壊れやすくなるものなのよ
Really?
えっ そうなの？
The server load grows proportionally.
サーバー:server, 負荷[ふか]:burden/load (e.g. cpu time, electricity, etc.), 大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great
（フミエ）それだけ
サーバーの負荷も大きいし
Don't forget that Illegals infiltrate the servers illicitly,
イリーガル:illegal, 違法[いほう]:illegal/illegality/invalid, サーバー:server, 占有[せんゆう]:exclusive possession/occupation/monopolization
それに イリーガルって
違法にサーバーを占有してるから
so their bodies are constantly being deleted bit by bit.
しょっちゅう:always/constantly/frequently, 小刻み[こきざみ]:mincing|doing something repeatedly over a short interval (trembling, stepping quickly, etc.)|bit by bit, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 削除[さくじょ]:deletion/elimination/erasure
しょっちゅう小刻みに
体を削除されてるはずよ
Their bodies are... deleted?
体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 削除[さくじょ]:deletion/elimination/erasure
体を削除？
Even in the case of cyberpets,
ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, 場合[ばあい]:case/situation, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 細分化[さいぶんか]:fragmentation/subdivision/segmentation
（フミエ）
ペットの場合も体を細分化されて
their bodies are broken up into segments
which are handled on different servers.
あちこち:here and there/all around|to get things in the wrong order (back to front), 並列[へいれつ]:running in parallel/lined up alongside|parallel (electronics, computing, etc.), 処理[しょり]:processing/dealing with/treatment
あちこちで並列処理されてるの
If a server finds traces of an Illegal,
サーバー:server, イリーガル:illegal, 部品[ぶひん]:parts/accessories/components, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
どこのサーバーも
イリーガルの部品を見つけたら
it deletes them at once.
削除[さくじょ]:deletion/elimination/erasure
すぐに削除するわ
So then, its cry of pain...
時々[ときどき]:sometimes/at times, 苦しい[くるしい]:painful|needy|forced (smile, joke)||, 鳴く[なく]:to sing (bird)|to make sound (animal)|to make a meld call (e.g. pung, kong)
じゃあ 時々
苦しそうに鳴いてるのは…
...may be a cry of pain from having a bit of its body erased.
体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 削る[けずる]:to shave (wood, leather, etc.)|to cut down (budget, expenses, salary, etc.)|to delete, 削る[はつる]:to shave off (esp. concrete)|to take a percentage/to take a cut, 痛み[いたみ]:pain/ache|damage, 鳴く[なく]:to sing (bird)|to make sound (animal)|to make a meld call (e.g. pung, kong)
（フミエ）体を少しずつ削られる
痛みで鳴いてるのかもね
If it can actually feel pain, that is.
痛み[いたみ]:pain/ache|damage, 感じる[かんじる]:to feel/to sense/to experience, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
痛みを感じるとしたらの話だけど
Well, you know, you shouldn't get so attached to artificial life forms.
所詮[しょせん, そせん]:after all, 作り物[つくりもの]:artificial product|fiction|decoration (e.g. for a festival)||, 命[いのち]:life|lifetime|most important thing||, 命[めい]:command|life|destiny, あんまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), 感情移入[かんじょういにゅう]:empathy, 損[そん]:loss/damage|disadvantage
まあ 所詮(しょせん) 作り物の命よ
あんまり感情移入すると 損 損…
That's not true!
（デンパ）そんなことないよ！
I'm telling the truth.
ホント:truth/reality/actuality
（フミエ）
ホントのことを言ったまでよ
If it feels pain...
痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding
痛いなら… 痛いけど…
No, it does feel pain!
But if I tell it that I'm right here beside it,
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, さする:to pat/to stroke|to rub off
“僕も ここに一緒にいるぞ”って
さすってやれば
the pain eases a little!
痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding, 少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 減る[へる]:to decrease (in size or number)/to diminish/to abate
痛いのは少し減るんだ
That's what friends are for!
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
友達なら
そうしなきゃダメなんだ！
But all living things die someday.
生き物[いきもの]:living thing/animal
でも生き物は いつか死ぬのよ
Fumie...
（ヤサコ）フミエちゃん
I'm very busy with my summer course.
夏期[かき]:summer term (e.g. school)/summer period, 講習[こうしゅう]:short course/training, 忙しい[いそがしい, せわしい]:busy/occupied|restless
私 今 夏期講習で忙しいの
I only came here because I thought it would be something more interesting.
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant, 損する[そんする]:to lose (money, etc.)|to have wasted one's (time, etc.)/to have one's efforts come to naught
もっと面白いものかと思って
来たけど損しちゃった
Fumie...
少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, ネズミ:mouse/rat, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET
（ヤサコ）フミエちゃん 少し前に
ネズミのペット サッチーに…
You know,
Fumie once had a pet, but Satchii...
I know.
（デンパ）知ってる
It's just like Fumie said.
とおり:avenue/street|coming and going, とおり:penetration (as of light)
フミエの言うとおりだよ
誰でもいつかは死ぬんだ
Everyone has to die some day.
Yasako!
（デンパ）ヤサコ
んっ？　何？
What is it?
They're going to start building on this lot!
グラウンド:sports ground/sports oval, 建つ[たつ]:to be erected/to be built
このグラウンド
何かビルが建つんだ
You mean this place is going to disappear?!
なくなる:to die, なくなる:to be lost (e.g. luggage)/to be missing|to be used up
ここ なくなるの？
The construction will start...
工事[こうじ]:construction work/construction/work (related to construction, e.g. painting, concrete-pouring, etc.), 始まる[はじまる]:to begin|to happen (again)|to date (from), 明日[あした, あす]:tomorrow|near future
（デンパ）
工事が始まるのは… 明日だ！
tomorrow!
場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 移す[うつす]:to change|to change the object of one's interest or focus|to spend or take time||
（ハラケン）
なんとか別な場所に移すしかない
All we can do is move it someplace else.
（ヤサコ）イサコが言ってたわ
Isako said that
イリーガル:illegal, 普通[ふつう]:general|normally|local train, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 溶ける[とける]:to melt/to thaw/to fuse, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
“イリーガルは
普通の空間では溶けてしまう”って
if an Illegal is in a normal Space, it will disintegrate.
移動[いどう]:movement/transfer|mobile
じゃあ 移動もできないの？
So it can't move from here?
実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, 普通[ふつう]:general|normally|local train, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
（デンパ）
実は前 普通の空間に―
Actually,
there was one time when Plesio left this Space and entered a normal Space.
迷う[まよう]:to lose one's way|to waver|to give into temptation|, 出る[でる]:to leave|to leave (on a journey)|to move forward||, ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions
クビナガが
迷い出たことがあったんだ
（ヤサコ）どうなったの？
What happened?
やっと:at last/at length|barely, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
（デンパ）１時間して
やっと見つけたんだけど
I found it an hour later.
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 文字[もじ, もんじ]:letter (of alphabet)/character|literal, 化け[ばけ]:transforming oneself/taking on another form|artificial fly (for fishing), 痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding
確かに体が文字化けしてて
痛そうだった
I remember that its body was misencoded, and it seemed to be in a lot of pain.
どうしよう…
What can we do?
移動[いどう]:movement/transfer|mobile, 危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk
１時間か
移動させるには危険だな
An hour...
That's a dangerously long time if we want to move it.
放つ[はなつ]:to fire (gun, arrow, questions, etc.)|to set free|to emit (e.g. light)||, どのみち:anyway/anyhow/at any rate
でも このまま放っておいたら
どのみち…
But if we leave it like this,
it'll definitely...
決める[きめる]:to decide|to clinch (a victory)|to persist in doing||
決めたよ
ここには もういられない
I've made up my mind.
It can't stay here any longer.
苦しい[くるしい]:painful|needy|forced (smile, joke)||, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
苦しくても 別の場所を探そう
No matter how hard it is, let's find another place for it.
でも どこに？
But where?
It has to be an obsolete Space,
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 広い[ひろい]:spacious/vast/wide, 黒い[くろい]:black|dark|illicit, 地面[じめん]:ground/earth's surface
古い空間で広くて 黒い地面で
spacious, and on dark ground.
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 減る[へる]:to decrease (in size or number)/to diminish/to abate
（ヤサコ）ただでさえ
古い空間が減ってるのに…
To make things worse, all the obsolete Spaces are disappearing.
やっぱり:too/also|still, 簡単[かんたん]:simple/easy|brief, 見つかる[みつかる]:to be found/to be discovered
やっぱり
そう簡単には見つからないわ
As I thought, it's not so easy to find any at all.
感覚[かんかく]:sense/sensation/feeling
この感覚…
This feeling...
ひょっと:possibly/perhaps|unintentionally
ひょっとして…
Could it be...?
見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
見つけた
I've found it!
Great job, Yasako!
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength), 大手[おおて]:major company|front castle gate|force attacking the front of a castle, 大手[おおで]:full length of one's arm (from shoulder to fingertip), 柄[え]:handle/grip|stalk (of a mushroom, leaf, etc.), 柄[がら]:pattern|body build|essential qualities|
（ハラケン）
すごいよ ヤサコ
大手柄だ！
You're amazing!
偶然[ぐうぜん]:coincidence|by chance|contingency (philosophy)
（ヤサコ）ぐ… 偶然よ
I-It was just plain luck.
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks
（デンパ）
ヤサコ ありがとう
Yasako, thank you!
道筋[みちすじ]:path/route/itinerary
あとは道筋だな
Now we have to figure out a path.
白い[しろい]:white, 道路[どうろ]:road/highway, 使える[つかえる]:to be usable/to be serviceable/to be useful
そうか 白い道路も使えないものね
That's right, because we can't use any streets that are white.
見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||, 入り口[いりぐち, いりくち]:entrance/entry/gate
（ハラケン）ここが
ヤサコが見つけた道の入り口だ
This is the entrance to the path you found.
I think I just found a possible route.
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, 調べる[しらべる]:to examine/to investigate/to check up, 見込み[みこみ]:hope|expectation|side of a structural member, 道順[みちじゅん]:itinerary/route
さっき調べたら
見込みのある道順があった
実際[じっさい]:practicality|reality|bhutakoti (limit of reality)
実際に行ってみよう
Let's try a practice run.
一番[いちばん]:number one|best|game||, 一番[ひとつがい]:pair/couple/brace, 遠回り[とおまわり]:detour/roundabout way
一番 遠回りだけど
It happens to be the longest route,
ルート:root, ほとんど:mostly/nearly/practically, 路面[ろめん]:road surface, 真っ黒[まっくろ]:pitch black
このルートなら
ほとんどの路面が真っ黒だ
but almost all the streets' surfaces are completely black.
行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|
これで行けるぞ
It should be fine.
あら？
Eh?
道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||, 白い[しろい]:white, タイル:tile
（デンパ）
あっ 道が白いタイルになってる
Ah!
The pavement is being changed to white tiles!
市[いち]:market/fair, 市[し]:city, 方針[ほうしん]:objective/plan/policy
（ヤサコ）市の方針では―
According to the town plans,
全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, 白い[しろい]:white, タイル:tile, 敷き詰める[しきつめる]:to cover a surface/to spread all over/to blanket
ここは全部
白いタイルを敷き詰めるそうよ
this area will be tiled white.
そんな…
No way.
And to think I said it was the best route...
最高[さいこう]:most/highest|best, ルート:root
（ハラケン）
最高のルートだったのに
（ヤサコ）そうだ ハラケン
コネを使うのよ
Oh, yeah!
Haraken, use your connections.
コネ？
My connections?
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 管理[かんり]:control/management (e.g. of a business), 室[しつ]:room|wife (of someone of high rank)|scabbard|, 室[むろ]:greenhouse/icehouse/cellar, 玉子[たまご]:eggs|hen egg|(an expert) in the making|
はい 空間管理室の原川(はらかわ)玉子(たまこ)を…
Hello, I'd like to speak to Tamako Harakawa from the Cyberspace Management Bureau.
登校[とうこう]:attendance (at school)/going to school
えっ 登校日？
What? A school day?
女子高生[じょしこうせい]:female high-school student
（ヤサコ）オバちゃんって
女子高生だったのね
So your aunt studies at an all-girls school.
学校[がっこう]:school, 初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ...
（ハラケン）オバちゃんの学校
来たの初めてだ
This is the first time I've ever come to my aunt's school.
（オバちゃん）ケンちゃん
Ken!
（ハラケン）オバちゃん？
（ヤサコ）えっ これが？
Auntie?
B-But she...
（オバちゃん）
“これ”とは何よ “これ”とは
But what, huh? What?
年中[ねんじゅう, ねんちゅう]:whole year|always|middle class (of a nursery school, etc.), バイク:motorcycle/motorbike, 飛ばす[とばす]:to fly|to skip over|to run or drive fast||
私だって 年がら年中
バイク飛ばしてるわけじゃないわよ
You didn't seriously believe that I ride a bike all the time, did you?
用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|
で なんの用？
So what do you need?
実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|
実は…
Actually...
道路[どうろ]:road/highway, 客員[きゃくいん, かくいん]:guest (associate) member, 担当[たんとう]:being in charge (of an area of responsibility)/being responsible (for a work role, etc.)
道路？　私は客員だし
道路は担当じゃないのよね
A road?
I'm just an employee, and more importantly, roads don't fall under my domain.
頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
（ハラケン）
そこを頼むよ オバちゃん
But I'm begging you, Auntie.
いくら:how much?/how many?|even, 頼み[たのみ]:request/favor|reliance, 頼み[だのみ]:depending on/dependent upon
いくらケンちゃんの頼みでもムリ
Even if you ask me like that, there's nothing I can do about it.
頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
ていうか
なんで そんなこと頼むの？
Anyway, why are you asking me this?
そ… それは…
W-Well...
やっぱり:too/also|still
や… やっぱり なんでもない
Anyway, it's not really important!
ちょ… ちょっと！
H-Hey!
女子高生[じょしこうせい]:female high-school student, トラブル:trouble, 起こす[おこす]:to raise|to wake|to cause||
（一郎(いちろう)）あの女子高生が
トラブルを起こすせいで
Because that schoolgirl caused so much trouble here,
立場[たちば]:standpoint/position/situation, 弱い[よわい]:weak/frail/delicate
今 こっちは立場が弱いんだよ
I've lost face.
頼み[たのみ]:request/favor|reliance, 頼み[だのみ]:depending on/dependent upon, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
そんなこと頼みに行ったら
金沢(かなざわ)に帰れって言われちゃうよ
If I ask them to do such a thing, they'll send me straight back to Kanazawa.
トラブル:trouble
（ヤサコ）
そ… そのトラブルって？
By trouble, do you mean...?
駅[えき]:station, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 壊す[こわす]:to break|to wreck|to break (a bill, etc.)
（一郎）駅ビルの空間 壊したり
The Space failure incident at the station,
置き場[おきば]:place for something/storehouse, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 荒らす[あらす]:to lay waste|to invade|to troll (e.g. web forums)
バス置き場の空間 荒らしたり
the Space distortion at the bus graveyard,
街中[まちなか]:downtown, 街中[まちじゅう]:the whole town/all over the town/throughout the town, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 沈める[しずめる]:to sink/to submerge|to floor (an opponent)
街中 電脳の水で沈めたり
the inundation of cyberwater all over town...
やっぱ:too/also|still
あっ やっぱいいわ…
Ah, it's not important after all!
普段[ふだん]:usual/habitual/ordinary, 行い[おこない]:deed/act/action, 裏目に出る[うらめにでる]:to backfire/to produce a result opposite to what was expected or intended
（ヤサコ）
普段の行いが裏目に出たわ
Our actions have come back to haunt us...
完成[かんせい]:complete/completion|perfection, 通る[とおる]:to go by|to run (between)|to go indoors||
完成前に なんとか通るしかない
We need to get through somehow before the construction is finished.
実行[じっこう]:practice/practising/performance
もう時間がないわ 実行しましょう
We're running out of time.
We need to act.
連れる[つれる]:to lead/to take (a person), 移動[いどう]:movement/transfer|mobile, 初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ...
（ハラケン）クビナガを連れて
移動するのは初めてだな
This is the first time I've taken Plesio with me.
（ヤサコ）どう？
Well?
It's not as bad as I thought.
（デンパ）
うん 思ったより大丈夫
体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great, 小さい[ちいさい]:small/little/tiny, イリーガル:illegal
（ハラケン）体が大きいから
小さいイリーガルよりは―
Since its body is large,
it can probably resist longer than the smaller Illegals.
耐える[たえる]:to bear|to support|to be fit for, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
耐えられるのかもしれない
Let's go, Plesio.
さあ行こう クビナガ
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, ダメージ:damage
（ハラケン）
新しい空間だけでもダメージなのに
Not only is the new Space inflicting damage,
白い[しろい]:white, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||, 厄介[やっかい]:trouble/burden|care
白い道まであると厄介だな
but the streets with white surfaces make it especially hard, too.
What about the places where the distinction between black and white isn't so clear?
白黒[しろくろ]:black and white/monochrome|good and evil, はっきり:clearly/plainly|to be clear, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
（ヤサコ）白黒はっきりしない所は
どうなのかしら？
街頭[がいとう]:in the street, カメラ:camera, 黒[くろ]:black|black go stone|guilt, っぽい:-ish/-like|tossing something out, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
（ハラケン）街頭カメラから見て
黒っぽく見えるかどうかだから
The dark tones are spotted by external cameras.
日光[にっこう]:sunlight, 角度[かくど]:angle
日光の角度によっては…
So, depending on the sunlight's angle...
商店街[しょうてんがい]:shopping district/shopping street/downtown, 裏[うら]:bottom (or another side that is hidden from view)|rear|lining||, 路地[ろじ]:alley|bare earth (i.e. ground not covered by a roof)|teahouse garden|
商店街はムリだ
（ヤサコ）裏路地を行きましょう
We can't pass through the commercial district.
Let's take the back streets.
路面[ろめん]:road surface, 自体[じたい]:itself|one's own body|originally, 黒い[くろい]:black|dark|illicit
（ハラケン）
路面自体は黒いんだけど
The road itself is black,
角度[かくど]:angle, 白い[しろい]:white, 輝く[かがやく]:to shine/to glitter/to sparkle, ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions
角度によっては白く輝くことがある
but in some areas it has white patches.
サーバー:server, 色[いろ]:colour|complexion|appearance||, 色[しょく]:counter for colours, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
サーバーに そっちの色が
入ってしまっているんだ
That's the color the server has recorded.
マズい:unappetising|unskillful|ugly|
（電子音）
（ヤサコ）あっ マズい！
Oh no!
ハ… ハラケン！
Haraken!
待て！
Wait!
ハァ…
You're the best in this sort of situation.
頼もしい[たのもしい]:reliable/trustworthy|hopeful
ハラケンがいると
こういうとき頼もしいわ
A minute later
Wait!
待て！
Another minute later
Wait!
（ハラケン）待て！
キ… キリがないわ
There's no end to them!
Me Satchii!
（サッチー）ボク サッチー
待て！
Wait!
止まる[とまる]:to stop (moving)|to stop (doing, working, being supplied)|to alight, 止まる[とどまる]:to remain/to abide|to be limited to
止まらない！
（ヤサコ）なんで？
It's not stopping!
Why?
Run for it!
逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
逃げよう！
とても:very/awfully|(not) at all
（ヤサコ）と… とてもムリだわ
It's impossible.
And the construction is progressing rapidly.
工事[こうじ]:construction work/construction/work (related to construction, e.g. painting, concrete-pouring, etc.), どんどん:drumming (noise)|rapidly/steadily, 進む[すすむ]:to advance|to precede|to make progress||, 進む[すさむ]:to grow wild/to run to waste
（ハラケン）
工事もどんどん進んでる
このままじゃ
ここからも出られなくなるわ
At this rate, it won't be able to leave here at all.
We have to buy some time
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, ルート:root, 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 時間を稼ぐ[じかんをかせぐ]:to gain time/to play for time/to buy time
新しいルートを探す間
なんとか時間を稼がないと
while we search for a new route.
I've heard all about it.
話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
（フミエ）話は聞いたわ
（３人）フミエちゃん！　フミエ！
Fumie!
No way around it. I'll help you out.
しょう:workman/artisan|craft, しょう:quotient|dealing/dealer, 手伝う[てつだう]:to help/to assist|to contribute to
（フミエ）
しょうがないから手伝ってやるわ
All we need to do is interfere with the construction, right?
工事[こうじ]:construction work/construction/work (related to construction, e.g. painting, concrete-pouring, etc.), 妨害[ぼうがい]:disturbance/obstruction/hindrance
工事の妨害をすればいいんでしょ？
That's my specialty!
得意分野[とくいぶんや]:one's field of expertise
私の得意分野よ
Will you really help us?
手伝う[てつだう]:to help/to assist|to contribute to
（デンパ）手伝ってくれるの？
（フミエ）ま… まあね
Y-You could say that.
But Denpa,
ただし:but/however/provided that, デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception
（フミエ）ただし デンパ！
I'm gonna tax you 10% of the metabugs you collect from now on.
今後[こんご]:from now on/hereafter, 集める[あつめる]:to collect/to assemble/to gather, 割[わり]:rate|profit|assignment||, 上納[じょうのう]:payment to the government
今後は集めたメタバグを
１割 上納すること
What kind of person are you?
あんたって人は…
Well? Do you think we can find one?
見つかる[みつかる]:to be found/to be discovered
（デンパ）どう？　見つかりそう？
We've searched everywhere, but...
散々[さんざん]:thoroughly|severely|scattered, 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
（ヤサコ）散々 探したけど…
There just isn't a path we can use.
使える[つかえる]:to be usable/to be serviceable/to be useful, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||, 見つかる[みつかる]:to be found/to be discovered
（ハラケン）
使える道が見つからない
I wonder how Fumie is doing?
かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
（ヤサコ）フミエちゃんのほうは
どうかしら？
If you don't stop construction, my blood will be on your hands!
中止[ちゅうし]:suspension/stoppage/discontinuance, 祟る[たたる]:to curse/to cast a spell|to cause a bad result
（フミエ）
中止しないと祟(たた)ってやるう～
Sold Out
Damn!
（フミエ）この… この…
この… この…
Damn!
Can she really slow the construction down by doing that?
ホント:truth/reality/actuality, 工事[こうじ]:construction work/construction/work (related to construction, e.g. painting, concrete-pouring, etc.), 遅れる[おくれる]:to be late/to be delayed/to fall behind schedule, かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
あれでホントに
工事 遅れるのかしら？
I found some information today.
情報[じょうほう]:information/news|information
（フミエ）今日 情報が入ったわ
Tomorrow, at 3am,
明日[あした, あす]:tomorrow|near future, 午前[ごぜん]:morning/a.m., グラウンド:sports ground/sports oval, ドメイン:domain
明日の午前３時に
グラウンドのドメインが―
the lot's domain will become accessible to Satchii.
入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||, 種類[しゅるい]:variety/kind|counter for different sorts of things, 変更[へんこう]:change/modification/alteration
サッチーにも入れる種類に
変更される
That means...
（ハラケン）じゃあ…
...Plesio can only stay there
あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals
クビナガが
あそこにいられるのは―
until then.
時刻[じこく]:instant/time/moment
その時刻までよ
If only it could cross this bridge,
橋[はし]:bridge, 橋[きょう]:pons (pontes)/pons Varolii/pontine, 渡る[わたる]:to cross over/to go across|to extend, いくつ:how many?|how old?, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||
この橋さえ渡れれば
いくつか道があるのに
we'd have plenty of paths for it to go...
But every bridge has a white surface.
橋[はし]:bridge, 橋[きょう]:pons (pontes)/pons Varolii/pontine, 白い[しろい]:white, 路面[ろめん]:road surface, ばかり:only/merely|approximately
（ハラケン）
橋は どれも白い路面ばかりだし…
夜[よる, よ]:evening/night, 夜[や]:counter for nights
（フミエ）夜は？
And at night?
It's useless.
街灯[がいとう]:street light, すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength), 明るい[あかるい]:bright|cheerful|familiar (with)|
（ヤサコ）
ダメ 街灯がすごく明るいの
The street lamps are too bright.
あっ そうだ
（ヤサコ）どうしたの？
That's it!
What is it?
We'll have it go across the water!
水面[すいめん, みなも]:water's surface, 渡る[わたる]:to cross over/to go across|to extend
水面を渡るんだ
（ヤサコ）水面？
The water?
But look how it shines.
光る[ひかる]:to shine/to glitter/to be bright
でも こんなに光ってるわよ
At night, the water's surface is completely black.
夜[よる, よ]:evening/night, 夜[や]:counter for nights, 水面[すいめん, みなも]:water's surface, 真っ黒[まっくろ]:pitch black
夜の水面は真っ黒だよ
（３人）あっ！
All right!
よーし:alright/all right/right on, 明日[あした, あす]:tomorrow|near future, 朝[あさ, あした]:morning, 朝[ちょう]:dynasty|reign|period||, 決行[けっこう]:doing (with resolve)/carrying out (e.g. a plan)
（フミエ）よーし！
明日の朝 ３時ちょっと前に決行よ
Let's commence the plan tonight before 3am!
Yeah!
ハァー！
All right! With these high spirits, let's go!
はりきる:to be in high spirits/to be full of vigor (vigour)/to be enthusiastic
さあ はりきっていこう！
We're sleepy...
眠い[ねむい]:sleepy/drowsy/somnolent
（３人）眠い…
夜中[よなか]:middle of the night/dead of night, 夜中[やちゅう]:during the night/at night, 工事[こうじ]:construction work/construction/work (related to construction, e.g. painting, concrete-pouring, etc.)
（ヤサコ）な… なんで
こんな夜中に工事してるの？
Why are they still working at this late hour?!
They want to make up the time they lost by working at night!
工事[こうじ]:construction work/construction/work (related to construction, e.g. painting, concrete-pouring, etc.), 遅れ[おくれ]:delay/lag/postponement, 夜間[やかん]:at night/nighttime, 作業[さぎょう]:work/operation/manufacturing, 取り戻す[とりもどす]:to take back/to regain/to get back, 気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of
工事の遅れを
夜間作業で取り戻す気だ
マズい:unappetising|unskillful|ugly|, 急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten
マズいわ 急ぎましょう
Uh-oh.
Let's hurry!
It can't go any further!
通る[とおる]:to go by|to run (between)|to go indoors||
通れなくなってる
ドメイン:domain, 切り替わる[きりかわる]:to change completely/to switch (to)/to shift (to another mode)
ドメインが
もう切り替わりつつあるんだ
The domain is already starting to change!
黒[くろ]:black|black go stone|guilt, 広げる[ひろげる]:to spread|to unfold|to scatter about|
黒バグを使って広げるのよ
We'll have to expand the Space by using kurobugs.
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception, 急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten
デンパ 急げ！
Denpa, quickly!
The kurobugs will attract Kyuu-chans!
黒[くろ]:black|black go stone|guilt, 引きつける[ひきつける]:to fascinate/to attract|to have a convulsion
黒バグに引きつけられて
キュウちゃんが来るぞ
うん… クビナガ！
Plesio...
来たわ！
They're here!
狭い[せまい]:narrow/confined/small, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
（ハラケン）
ダメだ ここは狭すぎる
It's no good! It's too narrow!
（フミエ）あっ サッチーだわ！
It's Satchii!
しかたない:it can't be helped/it's inevitable/it's no use, 強力[きょうりょく]:powerful/strong, 強力[ごうりき]:herculean strength/mountain carrier-guide, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
しかたない
ちょっと強力すぎるけど…
I have no choice.
It might be a bit too powerful, but...
下がる[さがる]:to come down|to hang|to move back||
下がって！
Stay back!
待て！
Wait!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
みんなも早く！
Everyone, hurry!
Are you okay?
大丈夫？
The first barrier.
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 関門[かんもん]:barrier/checkpoint|hurdle
（ハラケン）第１の関門だ
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
（うめき声）
（デンパ）クビナガ 頑張るんだ！
Plesio, you can do it!
Now for the second barrier.
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 関門[かんもん]:barrier/checkpoint|hurdle
（ハラケン）第２の関門だ
Oh?
なくなる:to die, なくなる:to be lost (e.g. luggage)/to be missing|to be used up
あれ？　なくなったわ
It's empty...
Plesio, you can do it!
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
クビナガ 頑張るんだ！
Watch out!
危ない[あぶない]:dangerous|in danger|uncertain||
（ハラケン）危ない！
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception
（ヤサコ）デンパ君！
Denpa, watch out!
Plesio!
クビナガ！
Plesio, hang in there!
しっかり:tightly (holding on)/firmly|strongly (built)
クビナガ しっかり…
Is it far?
ねえ まだなの？
Don't worry, we're almost there.
少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance
だ… 大丈夫 もう少しよ
Thank goodness!
少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance
よかった
もう少しだよ クビナガ
It's only a bit further, Plesio.
Haraken...
ハラケン…
Because it's been in a new Space for some time,
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
新しい空間に長くいたせいで
the damage inflicted by the white surface is spreading.
白い[しろい]:white, 地面[じめん]:ground/earth's surface, ダメージ:damage, 大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great
白い地面のダメージも
大きくなっている
But...
（ヤサコ）そんな…
It probably won't last much longer...
多分[たぶん]:perhaps/probably|generous
（ハラケン）
多分 もう長くはもたない
...whether we reach the new site or not.
たどり着く[たどりつく]:to arrive at (after a struggle)/to finally reach/to find one's way to, 着く[つく]:to arrive at/to reach|to sit on, 着く[はく]:to put on (or wear) lower-body clothing (i.e. pants, skirt, etc.)|to affix a sword to one's hip|to affix a bowstring to a bow
たどり着いても 着かなくても…
It's dawn!
夜明け[よあけ]:dawn/daybreak
（フミエ）夜明けよ！
（２人）ハッ！
Let's hurry!
急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten
急ごう
So we didn't make it in time...
間に合う[まにあう]:to be in time for|to serve (suit, meet) the purpose/to be good enough
間に合わなかったんだわ
Don't talk nonsense!
強行[きょうこう]:forcing/enforcement|forced
バカ言わないで！　強行するのよ
We're going through!
But at this rate, it'll die!
（ヤサコ）だけど
そんなことしたら―
I'm sorry.
ごめんよ… ごめんよ クビナガ
しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
死んでしまうわ
ごめんよ… ごめんよ クビナガ
I'm sorry, Plesio.
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
（フミエ）
このまま待ってても
同じことよ
Plesio?
クビナガ？
（デンパ）あっ 待って！
Wait!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 呼び戻す[よびもどす]:to call back/to call home
（ヤサコ）ど… どうしよう？
（ハラケン）早く呼び戻すんだ！
What can we do?!
Hurry! We've got to get it back here!
Plesio!
（デンパ）クビナガ！
PLESIO!
クビナガ～！
It couldn't be helped...
しかたない:it can't be helped/it's inevitable/it's no use
しかたなかったのよ
This just means that it wasn't strong enough to survive.
生き延びる[いきのびる]:to survive/to live long, 足りる[たりる]:to be sufficient|to be worth doing|to be sufficient
生き延びる力が
足りなかったってことよ
After all, it's only an artificial lifeform!
所詮[しょせん, そせん]:after all, 作り物[つくりもの]:artificial product|fiction|decoration (e.g. for a festival)||, 命[いのち]:life|lifetime|most important thing||, 命[めい]:command|life|destiny
所詮 作り物の命なのよ！
And it's an Illegal.
イリーガル:illegal, 感情移入[かんじょういにゅう]:empathy, 損[そん]:loss/damage|disadvantage
それもイリーガルよ
感情移入したら損なだけよ！
That's what happens when you get attached to something!
It was...
（ハラケン）あいつは…
Plesio must've felt very sad after being alone for so long.
ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 独りぼっち[ひとりぼっち, ひとりぽっち]:aloneness/loneliness/solitude, 寂しい[さびしい, さみしい]:lonely/lonesome/solitary
クビナガは ずっと独りぼっちで
寂しかったんじゃないかな
It really did
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
きっと仲間と同じ場所に
行きたかったんだ
want to reach its family.
In the direction Plesio had desperately run
暴走[ぼうそう]:acting rashly|runaway (process)|reckless baserunning, 行く手[ゆくて]:one's way/one's path
（ヤサコ）クビナガが暴走した
その行く手には―
stood an abandoned factory, its eerie chimneys standing in a line.
工場[こうじょう, こうば]:factory/plant/mill, 煙突[えんとつ]:chimney/smokestack|carrying a passenger without turning on the taximeter, 立ち並ぶ[たちならぶ]:to stand in a row (e.g. shops on a street)/to line in a row|to be equal to
使われなくなった工場の
オバケ煙突が立ち並んでいました
They looked like a herd of Plesios.
まるで:quite/entirely|as if, たくさん:a lot/lots|enough
それは まるで
たくさんのクビナガのようでした
I heard that a few days later,
工場[こうじょう, こうば]:factory/plant/mill, 煙突[えんとつ]:chimney/smokestack|carrying a passenger without turning on the taximeter, 群れ[むれ]:group/crowd/flock, 取り壊し[とりこわし]:demolition/pulling down/destruction
工場とその煙突の群れが
取り壊しになったのは
the factory and its line of chimneys were destroyed.
数[しばしば]:often/again and again/frequently, 数[かず]:number/amount, 後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|
それから
数日後のことだったそうです
Preview
Next time on Dennou Coil:
Chronicles of the Living Creature.
Chronicles of the
Living Creature
See you next time!
次回[じかい]:next time (occasion), 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, コイル:coil
（ヤサコ）
次回 「電脳コイル」
いきもの:living thing/animal, 記録[きろく]:record|record (e.g. in sports)|to record|
〝いきものの記録 〞
楽しみ[たのしみ]:enjoyment/pleasure|anticipation
お楽しみに